Miniature Book Society mss., LMC 2374
Lilly Library
Miniature Book Society mss.
1983-2011
Lilly Library
Miniature Book Society
LMC 2374
14 Boxes
This collection consists of the records of the Miniature Book Society, 1983-2011. The collection includes business files, traveling exhibition papers, correspondence, meeting minutes, souvenirs, manuscripts, catalogs, and audiovisual materials.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Historical Note
The Miniature Book Society was founded and chartered in 1983 in the state of Ohio and incorporated in the state of Delaware in July 1989.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically by year, following the General papers. Within each year the files are arranged alphabetically. Conclave keepsakes are filed separate boxes. Additions are arranged into 8 subseries: Business Files, Conclaves, Exhibitions, Catalogs, Publications, Dawson Papers, Ephemera, and Audiovisual. Each subseries is arranged chronologically by year, with the exception of Publications, which is arranged alphabetically by title.
Scope and Content Note
This collection consists of the records of the Miniature Book Society. The collection includes business files, traveling exhibition papers, and correspondence.
This collection is organized by year. Business files include minutes of board meetings and membership meetings; financial reports; committee reports; by-laws and by-law changes; publicity and newsletter guidelines; and publicity. Competition and traveling exhibition papers include entry forms; news releases and publicity; catalog of entries in book competition; and locations of traveling exhibition. Conclave materials include programs; lists of registrants; publicity; maps; and planning notes. Correspondence is mostly among board members, but also contains letters from entrants in the book competition and institutions interested in the traveling exhibition.
Additions consist of more business files, including many financial documents. Conclaves include board meeting minutes, various advertisements, correspondence, and souvenirs. Exhibitions are largely traveling exhibition correspondence, publicity, and planning. Catalogs include both facsimiles and physical copies of exhibition catalogs. Publications consist of correspondence, financial documentation, manuscripts, and audiovisual materials pertaining to titles published by the Miniature Book Society. The Dawson Papers are specific to Glen and Mary Helen Dawson, active members of the Miniature Book Society, and include Conclave related papers arranged by year. Ephemera include bags, folders, pencils, pins, souvenirs etc. collected at Conclaves. Audiovisual consists of photographs taken at Conclaves and CD-ROMs of catalog layouts and meeting minutes.
Correspondents include: Glen and Mary Helen Dawson, Joan Knoertzer, Twyla Muller Racz, and Mark Palkovic.
Acquisition Information
Gift. 1996, 1997, 2001, 2002, 2008, 2010, 2011, 2012, 2015
Miniature books --Societies.; Miniature Book Society.
- Business Files
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically by year, following the General papers. Within each year the files are arranged alphabetically. Conclave keepsakes are filed in a separate box.
  - General. Brochures concerning joining MBS and the traveling exhibition; logo design; book competition and traveling exhibition guidelines. Legal papers, including articles of incorporation; tax forms; correspondence with lawyer (2 folders) (see also: Oversize) (Box 1)
  - , Business; Conclave I - Dayton, OH; correspondence; directory of members, 1983; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Conclave planning materials, 1983-1991; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Business; Conclave II - Boston, MA; correspondence; directory of members, 1984; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Business; Conclave III - Burbank, CA; correspondence, 1985; (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Business; Conclave IV - Washington, D.C.; correspondence, 1986; (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Business; Conclave V - Chicago (Skokie), IL; correspondence, 1987; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Business; competition; Conclave VI - San Antonio, TX; correspondence, 1988; (5 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Traveling exhibition [1st], 1988-1989; (1 folder) (Box 1)
  - , Business; certificates of appreciation, 1989; (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - , Competition; Conclave VII - Cincinnati, OH; correspondence, 1989; (5 folders) (Box 2)
  - , Traveling exhibition [2nd], 1989-1990; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - , Business; certificates of appreciation; competition; Conclave VIII - Glasgow, Scotland; correspondence, 1990; (8 folders) (Box 2)
  - , Center for the Study of the Miniature Book, 1990-1991; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - , Traveling exhibition [3rd], 1990-1991; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - , Business; certificates of appreciation (scrapbook); competition; Conclave IX - Williamsburg, VA; correspondence, 1991; (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - , Traveling exhibition [4th], 1991-1992; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - , Business; competition; Conclave X - San Diego, CA; correspondence, 1992; (4 folders) (Box 2)
    General
    See also: Oversize
  - , Newsletter. July and Oct. issues, 1992; (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - , Traveling exhibition [5th], 1992-1993; (1 folder) (Box 2)
  - , Business; certificates of appreciation; competition; Conclave XI - Chicago, IL; correspondence, 1993; (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - , Newsletter. Jan., Apr., July and Oct. issues, 1993; (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Traveling exhibition [6th], 1993-1994; (1 folder) (Box 3)
  - , Business (Conclave XII - Ottawa, Ontario); competition (7th); correspondence, 1994; (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Newsletter. Jan., Apr., July and Oct. issues, 1994; (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Business (Conclave XIII - Pasadena, CA); competition and traveling exhibition (8th); correspondence, 1995; (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Newsletter. Jan., Apr. and July issues, 1995; (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Business; competition and traveling exhibition (9th); Conclave XIV - San Francisco, CA; correspondence, 1996; (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Business; competition and traveling exhibition(10th); Conclave XV - Bethlehem, PA; correspondence, 1997; (10 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Awards; business; competition (11th); Conclave XVI - Charleston, SC; correspondence; publicity, 1998; (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - , Conclave XVI - Charleston, SC (cont.); correspondence; publicity, 1998; (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - , Business (Conclave XVII - Germany/"Rump" Conclave in California); correspondence; traveling exhibition (12th), including videotape, 1999; (3 folders) (Box 4)
  - , Business (Conclave XVIII - Rutland, Vermont); correspondence, 2000; (2 folders) (Box 4)
  - , Business. Includes photographs and negatives from past Conclaves, 2001 (Box 4)
  - ,, Membership Directories, 1987; 1990 (Box 4)
  - ,,,,,,,,, Yearbooks (formerly: Membership Directory), 1991; 1992; 1993; 1994; 1995; 1997; 1998; 1999; 2000 (Box 4)
- Additions
  Arranged into 8 subseries: Business Files, Conclaves, Exhibitions, Catalogs, Publications, Dawson Papers, Ephemera, and Audiovisual.
  - Business Files
    - Financial statements, 1984-1994 (Box 4)
    - Check registers, 1988-1995 (Box 4)
    - Bank statements, 1985-1988 (Box 4)
    - Expenditures and income, 1989-1995 (Box 4)
    - Bank statements, 1992-1995 (Box 4)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 4)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 5)
    - 1996-1999 (Box 5)
    - 2000 (Box 5)
    - 2013 (Box 5)
    - Undated (Box 5)
  - Conclaves
    - II 1984, IX 1991, X 1992, XVI 1998, XVII 1999, XXIII 2005 (Box 5)
    - XXIV Ann Arbor, MI 2006, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Exhibitions
    - 1999, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - 2001, (3 folders) (Box 5)
    - 2005 (Box 5)
    - 2009-2010 (Box 5)
    - 2011, (5 folders) (Box 5)
    - 2012 (Box 6)
  - Catalogs
    - Facsimiles, 1991-2010 (Box 6)
    - 2009, (10 catalogs) (Box 6)
    - 2011, (7 catalogs) (Box 6)
    - 2012, (4 catalogs) (Box 6)
  - Publications
    - Between Earth, Sea, & Sky (Box 7)
    - Cabin in the Clearing (Box 7)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes floppy disc
    - Grande Dame (Box 7)
      Includes CD-ROM
    - Many Littles Makes a Much (Box 7)
    - Newsletters and additional associated papers, 2002, 2005 (Box 7)
    - A Scottish Tale (Box 7)
  - Dawson Papers
    - Business files (Box 8)
    - Conclave I Tipp City, OH, 1983 (Box 8)
    - Conclave II Boston, MA, 1984 (Box 8)
    - Conclave III Burbank, CA, 1985 (Box 8)
    - Conclave IV Washington, D.C., 1986 (Box 8)
    - Conclave V Skokie, IL, 1987 (Box 8)
    - Conclave VI San Antonio, TX, 1988 (Box 8)
    - Conclave VII Cincinnati, OH, 1989 (Box 8)
    - Conclave VIII Glasgow, Scotland, 1990 (Box 8)
    - Conclave IX Williamsburg, VA, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Conclave X San Diego, CA, 1992 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XI Chicago, IL, 1993 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XII Ottawa, Ontario, 1994 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XIII Pasadena, CA, 1995 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XIV San Francisco, CA, 1996 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XV Bethlehem, PA, 1997 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XVII Mission Hills, CA, 1999 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XXI Toronto, Canada, 2003 (Box 8)
    - Conclave XXVIII Lexington, KY, 2010 (Box 8)
  - Ephemera
    - Conclave keepsakes (including pencils, nametags, folders, etc.) (Box 9)
    - Membership directory (Box 9)
    - Documentation for certificates awarded in 1992 (Box 10)
    - Proofs and negatives from 1992 Conclave X (San Diego, CA) (Box 10)
    - MBS canvas bag (Box 10)
    - Conclave XXIX Dublin, Ireland 2011 messenger bag (Box 11)
      Filled with conclave pamphlets and souvenirs
    - Conclave keepsakes - miniature books, crafting kits, and addresses, 1984-1989? (Box 12-15)
    - Photo album, "the first Conclaves", 1983? (Box 16)
    - Silver engraved Glasgow Cup (Box 17)
      Donated by Helen and Ian MacDonald, this award was given for the first time in 1990 during Conclave VIII in Glasgow, Scotland. The cup honors an MBS member for their exemplary service
  - Audiovisual
    - Assorted CD-ROMs and audio-visual materials (Box 9)